All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף Daf in the
בבלי Bavli is י"א. Yud Alef. We pick up on the bottom
here on י' עמוד ב', Yud Amud Bet, זמן... Zeman... okay. So
תנו רבנן, Tanna Rabbanan, last line, and we're dealing with עיבור השנה.
Ibbur Hashana. אין מעברין את השנה אלא במזומנין. Ain me'abrin et hashana
ella bimezumamin. So look at this, right? Everybody just came from the
בבלי, Bavli, from the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, starts with the same point. The
only people who can participate are people that have been appointed. מעשה
ברבן
גמליאל, Ma'aseh beRabban Gamliel, it's going to see how fast this is
going to go now that you saw the story in the ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. מעשה ברבן גמליאל שאמר השכימו לי שבעה לעליה. Ma'aseh beRabban Gamliel
she'amar hishkimu li shiva l'aliyah.
Bring to me, it's interesting to say השכימו, hishkimu, we're going to
do it nice and early. Okay? Call for me seven people. השכימו
מצא שמונה. Hishkimu matza shemonah. He got up there and he found
eight had been gathered. אמר מי הוא שעלה שלא ברשות ירד. Amar
mi hu she'ala shelo birshut yeired. Who
is here without permission? Get out of here. אמר שמואל הקטן ואמר
אני הוא שעליתי שלא ברשות. Amar Shmuel Hakatan ve'amar ani hu she'aliti
shelo birshut.
It's me, though לא לעבר השנה עליתי, lo l'abber hashana aliti, I
wasn't here to participate in this thing, I wasn't called to do,
to do עיבור, ibbur, to do עיבור השנה, ibbur hashana, אלא ללמוד
הלכה למעשה הוצרכתי. ella lilmod halacha lema'aseh hitztarchti.
I need to learn some practical הלכה. halacha. Here רש"י Rashi says,
because the phrase is a little vaguer than the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, it
means I wanted to observe the proceedings. אמר לו שב בני שב,
Amar lo shev bni shev, sit my son, sit, ראויים כל השנים
כולן להתעבר על ידך, re'uyin kol hashanim kullan lehitabber al yadecha, you
are worthy of course to be on this בית דין beis din
all the years would be a fit to be done by you,
אלא אמרו חכמים אין מעברין את השנה אלא במזומנין, ella amru chachamim
ain me'abrin et hashana ella bimezumamin, but if you haven't been called,
you can't be a part of it, you can only do the
שנה, shana, the עיבור השנה ibbur hashana can only be by people
who have been appointed. ולא שמואל הקטן הוא, Velo Shmuel Hakatan hu,
אלא אלא איניש אחריני. ella ella inish achrini.
Now here's the בבלי Bavli and you can tell by the language,
the shift from the Hebrew to the Aramaic, it's adding in and
this clarifies that line in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. It wasn't really him.
He was the good guy. He was appointed. אלא איניש אחריני. ella
inish achrini. It was another guy who was there and didn't belong
there. ומחמת כיסופא הוא דעבד. Umachmat kisufa hu de'avid. He did it
to save the other guy the embarrassment. Okay, here becomes the whole
ethos of not snitching, right? And the teacher in the class sort
of says, okay, who threw the spitball? And nobody... everybody says, okay...
So,
it's maybe the opposite, not just not snitching, it's taking the blame.
Okay, כי הא דיתיב רבי, ki ha deyatv Rabbi, רבי, Rabbi, and
like another story, Michael remembered the story, רבי Rabbi was sitting וכד
דריש vekad darish and he was giving his שיעור, shiur, והריח ריח
שום vehariach rei'ach shum and he started smelling somebody had eaten garlic,
ugh. ואמר מי שאכל שום יצא, Ve'amar mi she'achal shum yetzei, who
is it who had garlic? Get out of here! I can't deal
with the smell of the garlic. עמד רבי חייא ויצא. Amad Rabbi
Chiya veyatza. So רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya got up and he left.
Okay, now once רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya left,
עמדו כולן ויצאו. amdu kullan veyatza. Everybody got up and left. Okay,
בשחר, beshachar, they better have done that because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
would have left and you still would have smelled the garlic if
the other guy was still there. Okay, בשחר beshachar
in the morning, מצא רבי שמעון ברבי, matza Rabbi Shimon b'Rabbi, רבי
שמעון ברבי Rabbi Shimon b'Rabbi son found the רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
אמר ליה amar lei and said to him, he thought רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya really did it. אתה הוא שציערת לאבא? Ata hu shetziaarta
le'abba? Why, I can't believe you caused my father that anguish, that
you didn't brush your teeth before coming to שיעור. shiur. אמר ליה
amar lei he said to him, לא תהא כזאת בישראל, lo tehei
kazot beYisrael, חס ושלום, chas veshalom, that wasn't me. Okay, I just
was doing it to protect the innocent. I was doing it to
protect the guilty, excuse me.
I took it differently. I always thought that it was אתה הוא
שציערת לאבא, ata hu shetziaarta l'abba, I know you didn't do it.
But rather, you caused everyone else to leave, because if you're going
to leave,
everyone else is going to leave. That's not what רש"י Rashi says.
That's what, no, God forbid, if someone should be embarrassed because of
this.
That's a nice read. Tell me what רש"י Rashi says. אתה הוא
שציערת לאבא, Ata hu shetziaarta l'abba, רש"י Rashi says שאכלת שום ונדף
הריח. she'achalta shum venadaf harei'ach. But I hear your read. Your read
is look, you caused the whole שיעור shiur to break up, and
he says I still wasn't going to let somebody be embarrassed. That's
a nice read. I like that read. Okay, לא תהא כזאת בישראל,
lo tehei kazot beYisrael,
which means sometimes it's more important to deal with, to suffer the
problem than to call somebody out and embarrass them. So then it
really would be a real critique of רבי, Rabbi, which is part
of the point though, by רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya choosing to leave,
he's really critiquing רבי Rabbi that you're not supposed to call somebody
out. Yeah, it just seems confusing in the context of the whole
discussion
about justice and it's like what does it mean? It's nice not
to embarrass someone but if we're having these stories about rabbis leaving
and being like, well then we don't know who's guilty.
Yeah,
but not everything is worthy of being brought to court and finding
guilt, right? This is more interpersonal. Like, I hope you don't live
your life by that, who's guilty, who's guilty, right? So it's about,
but you're right, I think thinking about that in juxtaposing it in
a whole context of it's all about guilt and innocence and thinking
about how human dynamics and relationships are not about that, right? You
know, like it's like, I actually recently wrote a פרשה שיעור parsha
shiur on this which and I titled it like, 'Would you rather
be happy or would you rather be right?' So you know, so
I maybe the other way, are you right or would you rather
be happy?
Like, the way I say that is, do I want to be
right or do I want to be married?
Exactly.
So anyway,
okay, so it says like this, but that's a very
good... Okay let's take רב חיים. Rav Chaim. Yeah so that's an
excellent point. Okay let's take רבי
חייא. Rabbi Chiya. מיהיכא גמר גמר? Meheicha gamar gamar? Where did רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiya learn to act this way? גמר לה מרבי מאיר.
Gamar lah mei-Rabbi Meir. He learned it from רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So now it's just going to show how there's a lot of,
you know, this good precedent for acting this way. דתניא. De-tanya. And,
you know, Erica's point might be a good one because maybe we
need to show precedent to this because somebody could say like this
is not about truth and this is not about justice, you know?
And that's the whole question about, you know, about that whole thing
about the non-snitch, the ethos of non-snitching, right? You're not supposed to
be a snitch or are you supposed to be truthful? Right? How
do you, when is it appropriate to say who did it and
when is it not appropriate? So I think that that's like a
good point. So in the whole context of דין, din, we want
to speak about, no, actually there are times about interpersonal and, you
know, human behavior where you're supposed to be acting this way. Okay.
רבי חייא מיהיכא גמר לה מרבי מאיר.
Rabbi Chiya meheicha gamar leh
mi-Rabbi Meir. דתניא. De-tanya. מעשה באשה אחת שבאה לבית מדרשו של רבי
מאיר. Maaseh be-isha achas she-ba'ah le-veis midrasho shel Rabbi Meir. A woman
came to the בית מדרש beis midrash of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
אמרה לו רבי אחד מכם קדשני בביאה. Amrah lo Rebbi echad mikem
kideshani be-bi'ah. One person from this בית מדרש beis midrash married me
with an act of intercourse, a sexual intercourse, which is, you're not
supposed to do קידושין kiddushin that way. עמד
רבי
מאיר וכתב לה גט כריתות. Amad Rabbi Meir ve-chasav lah get krisus.
So רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir
said, okay fine, it was me, and he wrote her a גט,
get, which is obviously a little dangerous because, you know, if he
would be now divorced and presumably knew it wasn't רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and the גט get wasn't going to do anything, but anyway
he was doing it because he got everybody else to do it.
עמדו וכתבו כולם ונתנו לה. Amdu ve-chasvu kulam ve-nasnu lah.
So that provided the cover for everybody now to write a גט.
get. So we're going to have everybody write this woman a גט
get so therefore nobody has to come forward and sort of take
the sort of blame on themselves, you know, and everybody will go
ahead and do it. So
he... yeah. Who paid the scribe? Exactly. So anyway, but there's, you
know, this way it was actually effective because it wasn't only saving
the person of embarrassment, it was also ensuring that the woman would
get her גט, get, right? If nobody would come forward and admit
to it, this woman would remain an עגונה. agunah. So like, he
managed to do two things, right? He managed to actually protect the
person and protect the woman. Okay. By the way, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir was a scribe, so maybe he was the one who did
it. Maybe actually the school was a scribal school and everybody was
an opportunity to practice their גט get writing. Okay. A scribal school.
No, exactly. Notice it said that they all wrote it. Maybe they
all wrote it themselves. ונתנו לה. Ve-nasnu lah. רבי מאיר מיהיכא גמר
לה? Rabbi Meir meheicha gamar leh? Where did he learn it? משמואל
הקטן. Mi-Shmuel HaKatan. From שמואל הקטן. Shmuel HaKatan. משמואל הקטן מיהיכא גמר
לה? Mi-Shmuel HaKatan meheicha gamar leh? משכניה בן יחיאל. Mi-Shechaniah ben Yechiel.
דכתיב, De-chasiv, like ויען
שכניה בן יחיאל מבני עילם ויאמר לעזרא אנחנו מעלנו באלהינו ונושב נשים
נכריות מעמי הארץ ועתה יש מקוה לישראל על זאת. Ve-ya'an Shechaniah ben
Yechiel mi-benei Elam va-yomer le-Ezra anachnu ma'alnu be-Eloheinu va-noshev
nashim nochriyos me-amei ha-aretz ve-ata yesh mikveh le-Yisrael al
zos. Okay, obviously he didn't marry a foreign wife but he spoke
in the plural, we have, in order to not like point out,
oh look these people, they're the רשעים, reshaim, they're the ones who
did it. All of these are a little different from one another.
These are not all exactly the same. Okay, you're talking obviously about
many many people that took foreign wives but still he's not dividing
it into the good guys versus the bad guys and pointing a
finger. He's speaking collectively.
שכניה בן יחיאל מיהיכא גמר לה? Shechaniah ben Yechiel meheicha gamar leh?
מיהושע. Mi-Yehoshua. Now this isn't what יהושע Yehoshua did, it's a story
about with יהושע. Yehoshua. ויאמר ה' אל יהושע קום לך למה זה
אתה נפל על פניך חטא ישראל. Va-yomer Hashem el Yehoshua kum lach
lamah zeh atah nofel al panecha chata Yisrael.
Israel has sinned. Okay, this was with עכן Achan taking from the
חרם, cherem, right? אמר לפניו רבונו של עולם מי חטא? Amar lefanav
Ribbono Shel Olam mi chata? Master of the universe, tell me who
was it? אמר לו וכי דילטור אני לך? Amar lo ve-chi diltor
ani lach? What, am am I your
tattletale? I don't know who has the Soncino, דילטור diltor has got
to be a Latin word or something. Yeah, it's delator. I know
what רש"י Rashi says, I'm wondering if what what the actual Latin
word is. Anyway, fine.
Am I some tattletale? Am I your snitch? וכי דילטור אני לך?
Ve-chi diltor ani lach? הטל גורלות. Hatel goralos. Go ahead, figure it
out for yourself, cast lots. So this is obviously a little bit
different because he did have to find out, right? It's all very
nice for the students to say I'm not snitching, but the teacher
wants to know who to punish. And if the teacher doesn't know
who to punish, maybe the whole class has to be punished, right?
So like this is an interesting case. God says I'm not going
to snitch, you figure it out for yourself. But in the end
there had to be a process, okay? Maybe the idea was that
through the process of doing the lots it gave the person the
opportunity to come forward, I don't know. But anyway,
right? ואיבעית אימא ממשה. Ve-iba'is eima mi-Moshe. Or he could learn it
from משה. Moshe. דכתיב, De-chasiv, עד אנה מאנתם, Ad anah me'antem, until
how long has it been that you're going to refuse to listen
to God by the taking of the מן? manna? And משה Moshe
spoke in this collective term, all of you, until how long are
all of you going to defy God? And it was only a
few people that went out to collect the מן. manna. Which also
raises questions, right? Because the flip side of not pointing out the
bad people is blaming everybody. and is collective punishment, like חטא ישראל
*Chata Yisrael*, right? So like, okay, it's very nice, like I said,
for the students to not snitch, but the teacher, "if you're not
going to tell me, then everybody's going to get punished," you know,
so it's like the interesting two sides of that. Okay. Now, תנו
רבנן Tanu rabanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*, we lost משמתו נביאים אחרונים חגי זכריה
ומלאכי נסתלקה רוח הקודש מישראל *mishemethu nevi'im acharonim Chaggai Zechariah u-Malachi nistalka
Ruach HaKodesh mi-Yisrael*. So after the end of the prophets, the heavenly
spirit departed. That's what it means by the end of the period
of prophets. ואף על פי כן היו משתמשים בבת קול *Ve-af al
pi chen hayu mishtamshim be-bat kol*. But even though they didn't have
direct prophecy, they would have like indirect, the heavenly voice, it says
like it's an echo maybe, you know, somehow, anyway, whatever exactly that
experientially was, it was some, you know, distant version of prophecy. פעם
אחת היו מסובים בעליית בית גוריא ביריחו *Pa’am achat hayu mesubin be-aliyat
Beit Gorya bi-Yericho*. This is going to tie into שמואל הקטן *Shmuel
HaKatan*. Anyway, they were once in the second story of this בית
בית גוריא *Beit Beit Gorya* in יריחו *Yericho*. ונתנה להם בת קול
מן השמים *Ve-nitna lahem bat kol min ha-shamayim* and they heard some
heavenly voice that said יש כאן אחד שראוי שתשרה עליו שכינה כמשה
רבינו *Yesh kan echad she-ra’uy she-tishreh alav Shechinah ke-Moshe Rabbeinu*. There's one
person here who's deserving that the divine presence rest on him on
משה *Moshe*. Now some people take out the word משה רבינו *Moshe
Rabbeinu* because they feel that that's heretical, because לא קם נביא עוד
בישראל כמשה *lo kam navi od be-Yisrael ke-Moshe*. But it doesn't say
that the person would have the same degree of prophecy as משה
רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu*, right? I mean to say that God's presence rests
on him does not mean the same thing as the same degree
of prophecy. But anyway, whatever it means. אלא *Ela*, but anyway שאין
דורו זכאי לכך *she-ein doro zakai le-kach*, it's not going to happen
because the generation does not merit it. ונתנו חכמים את עיניהם בהלל
הזקן *Ve-natnu chachamim et eineihem be-Hillel HaZaken*, so everybody looked at הלל
*Hillel*. They assumed it was talking about הלל *Hillel*. He is the
person that it is worthy of happening, but you know, we the
generation aren't worthy. וכשמת אמרו עליו *U-keshemet amru alav*, and when הלל
*Hillel* died they said about him, הי חסיד הי עניו *Hai chasid
hai anav*, woe to the righteous person, woe to the modest, תלמידו
של עזרא *talmido shel Ezra*, student of Ezra. It's interesting. They said
that he was as worthy as משה *Moshe*, but they called him
a student of Ezra, not a student because Ezra is of course
rabbinic Judaism. So they didn't call him a student of משה *Moshe*.
שוב פעם אחת *Shuv pa'am achat*, another time, היו מסובים בעליה ביבנה
*hayu mesubin be-aliya be-Yavne*. They were in יבנה *Yavne*. ונתנה להם בת
קול מן השמים *Ve-nitna lahem bat kol min ha-shamayim*, this was a
later generation, a heavenly voice came out, יש כאן אחד שראוי שתשרה
שכינה *Yesh kan echad she-ra’uy she-tishreh Shechinah*. One person is deserving of
the divine presence אלא שאין דורו זכאי לכך *ela she-ein doro zakai
le-kach*, but the generation is not worthy. ונתנו חכמים את עיניהם בשמואל
הקטן *Ve-natnu chachamim et eineihem bi-Shmuel HaKatan*. That's why we're telling the
story. They all looked at שמואל הקטן *Shmuel HaKatan*. So it's interesting,
he's called שמואל הקטן *Shmuel HaKatan*, and here he was, maybe the
reason he was called שמואל הקטן *Shmuel HaKatan* was because he was
so modest. He was the one that was saying, oh I wasn't
the one who was called, I just butted in here, you know?
Because of that previous story, look how great he really was. He
was the one that was worthy that the divine presence would rest
on him. וכשמת אמרו עליו הי חסיד הי עניו *U-keshemet amru alav
hai chasid hai anav*, and they said the same thing when he
died. Okay, תלמידו של הלל *talmido shel Hillel*, so הלל *Hillel* is
the student of Ezra and שמואל *Shmuel* is the student of הלל
*Hillel*. אף הוא אמר Omar בשעת מיתתו *Af hu amar bi-sh'at mitato*,
and now here even he שמואל *Shmuel* said at the moment of
his death, he himself had some like
divine, some insight into the future. And he said, שמעון וישמעאל לחרבא
*Shimon ve-Yishmael le-charba*, Shimon and Yishmael, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* and רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* who
was the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*, they will be by the sword.
This was right by the period of the Hadrianic persecutions. So he
was like seeing into the future and anticipating and seeing that this
was going to happen. וחברוהי לקטלא *Ve-chavrohi le-katla*, and their colleagues, you
know, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and all the others who died during
this period,
they will be murdered in another way. ושאר עמא לביזא *Ve-sha'ar ama
le-viza*, and the rest of the nation will be despoiled. ועקן סגיאן
עתידין למיתי על עלמא *Ve-akan sagiyan atidin le-meiti al alma*, and great
suffering will occur, will happen to the people, to the world. Okay,
so just and this apparently just demonstrates how he was ראוי שתשרה
שכינה *ra'uy she-tishreh Shechinah* that at the moment of his death, presumably
when he was like closest to God, his soul was about to
be with God, you know, this prophecy emerged. ועל יהודה בן בבא
*Ve-al Yehuda ben Bava*, now by רבי יהודה בן בבא *Rabbi Yehuda
ben Bava*, בקשו לומר כן *bikshu lomar ken*, they wanted to say
the same thing, הי חסיד הי עניו *hai chasid hai anav*, אלא
שנטרפה שעה *ela she-nitrefa sha’ah*, but the moment was snatched from them.
שאין מספידין על הרוגי מלכות *She-ein maspidin al harugei malchut*, because he
was one of the הרוגי מלכות *harugei malchut* and they were not
able to give a הספד *hesped*, you know, they didn't want to
get in trouble themselves with the Romans. They weren't able to give
a הספד *hesped*, a eulogy, for those that were killed by the
Romans. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*, so that was a fascinating
digression about this in about, led by the whole discussion about שמואל
*Shmuel* and not taking the blame and not pointing the finger. Now
we get back to the קידוש החודש *Kiddush HaChodesh*. תנו רבנן *Tanu
Rabbanan*,
or עיבור שנה ibur shana *ibbur shanah*. אין מעברין את השנה אלא
אם כן ירצה נשיא Nasi *Ein me'abrin et ha-shanah ela im ken
yirtzeh Nasi*. So we have the idea of appointment and now we're
having the idea that supposedly who the person is, who is appointing
it. It was רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* was the story
and so on. But here we have to say like the נשיא
Nasi, *Nasi* has to agree, not only appoint the people who are
part of the court, but he has to sort of sign off
on the decision, okay, to agree to do עיבור שנה ibur shana
*ibbur shanah*. אין מעברין את השנה אלא אם כן היתה דעת נשיא
Nasi ירצה נשיא Nasi. *Ein me'abrin et ha-shanah ela im ken hayeta
da'at Nasi yirtzeh Nasi*. מעשה ברבן גמליאל שהלך ליטול רשות אצל שלטון
אחד שבסוריה *Ma’aseh be-Rabban Gamliel she-halach litol reshut etzel shilton echad she-be-Surya*.
He went to get some permission some Roman officer in Syria
and he delayed coming back to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael. ועיברו את
השנה, ve'ibru et hashana, and then what are they going to do?
So they did עיבור שנה ibur shana. presumably they were people appointed
by him. Okay, but על מנת שירצה רבן גמליאל al menas sheyirtzeh
Rabban Gamliel on the condition that he would sign off on it.
וכשבא רבן גמליאל u'cheshebau Rabban Gamliel when he came, and by then
it was already in the middle of אדר שני, Adar Sheni, you
know, you have to do עיבור שנה ibur shana before אדר שני
Adar Sheni comes, but nevertheless he came, ואמר רוצה אני v'amar rotzeh
ani and he agreed, נמצא שנה מעוברת nimtza shana muberet so then
it retroactively validated what they had done. Even though the חידוש chiddush
here is that he didn't sign off on it before, he only
signed on it after it was, you know, too late to actually
do it. They had done it, but they stipulated on the condition
that he will eventually agree. And if he did then retroactively it
validated what they did.
Okay, what if he didn't agree?
What? Then retroactively they would have found themselves in the middle of
ניסן, Nissan, so I presume sounds like. תנו רבנן, אין מעברין את
השנה אלא אם כן הייתה צריכה מפני הדרכים ומפני דגשרים ומפני תנורי
פסחים. ein m'abrin et hashana ela im ken hayeta tzricha mipnei haderachim
umipnei degisharim umipnei tanurei pesachim. Now here are the factors that inform
whether you're going to do עיבור שנה. So it says it needs
it because the roads are muddy and people won't be able to
come up for עליה לרגל, Aliyah l'Regel, or because the, you know,
the bridges are washed out, or the ovens that you're going to
roast the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach in are all soggy and they
haven't dried out either. ומפני umipnei because they were outdoor ovens. גלויות
ישראל שנעקרו ממקומם ועדיין לא הגיעו. galuyot Yisrael shene'eku mimkomam v'adayin lo
higiyu. Or you know that people have been making their way from
to come up to do עליה לרגל, Aliyah l'Regel, but because of
various issues they have they're not going to get here in time.
So then you would add an extra month. אבל לא מפני השלג,
aval lo mipnei hasheleg, but if it's going to be snowy during
that period of ניסן, Nissan, that's not a good enough reason. People
will still come even through the snow. ולא מפני הצינה, v'lo mipnei
hatzina, or if it's too cold, that's not a good enough reason.
Oh, I want it to be nice and warm when they get
here. ולא מפני גלויות ישראל שלא עקרו ממקומם. v'lo mipnei galuyot Yisrael
shelo akru mimkomam. Or if you know that people are moving, people
aren't going to come, but they're not going to come because they
haven't gotten off their תחת. tuches. It's not that they're not going
to come because there was traffic, but because they haven't started mobilizing
when they should have started mobilizing, that's not a reason to do
to add an extra month. תנו רבנן, אין מעברין את השנה לא
מפני הגדיים ולא מפני הטלאים. ein m'abrin et hashana lo mipnei hag'daim
v'lo mipnei hatlaim. You don't do it because the goats or the
sheep are too small. You say, you know, let's give them another
month to grow up so קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, that's what they
come from, goats and sheep, people will bring a bigger animal for
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Nope, that's not a good enough reason. So
you bring a small animal. ולא מפני הגוזלות, v'lo mipnei hagozalot, or
not because the birds are too small because people bring the women
particularly would bring all the sacrifices for their childbirths they would wait
till they did עליה לרגל. Aliyah l'Regel. But let's say the birds
are still small because of the time it is during the year
they haven't, you know, matured enough. Nope, that's not a good enough
reason to postpone, you know, to add an extra month. שלא פרחו,
shelo pirchu, that they have not, you know, yet grown up. אבל
עושין אותם סעד לשנה, aval osin otam se'ad lashana, but you can
give it as an extra reason why you're adding. It can't be
the basis for adding, but you can give it as an extra
reason. סו כיצד, so keitzad, how would this be? רבי ינאי אומר
משום רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabi Yanai omer mishum Rabi Shimon ben
Gamliel, מהודעינן אנחנו לכון, mehodinan anachna lachon, this is fascinating, it seems
like we actually have the text that was actually used to issue
to make the declaration of עיבור שנה and here it was in
this Aramaic. We are informing you דגוזלניא רקיקין d'gozlanaya rakikin that the
birds are still tender, tender. ואימריא דארכין, v'imraya d'arkin, and the
and the sheep are still דקין dakim probably it should be a
sin, are small. וזימנא דאביבא לא מטא, v'zimna d'aviva lo mata, and
it's not yet the time of אביב, Aviv, the crops which is
the when the crops blossom, or whatever, you know, ripen, לא מטא,
lo mata, ושפיר מילתא באנפאי v'shapir miltza b'anpai and the matter is
good in our
eyes, ואוסיפנא על שתא דא תלתין יומין, v'osifna al shata da tlatin
yomin, thirty days. So that was like the official declaration. So that's
the idea of סעד לדברים. se'ad lidvarim. The real reason they're adding
it is because of אביב, Aviv, חודש אביב. Chodesh Aviv. It has
to be ניסן Nissan has to be when the grain is ripening.
But when they gave the reason, they added these as extra reasons
as well, but that really would not be sufficient for a basis
for adding the month. אוקיי מיתיבי, okay meitivei, now the problem is
it says you added thirty days, the extra אדר Adar was thirty
days. I'll ask you on this. It says כמה עיבור שנה שלשים
יום, kama ibur shana shloshim yom, thirty days. רבי שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר חודש, Rabi Shimon ben Gamliel omer chodesh, a month which is
twenty-nine days. And here it sounded like it was thirty days. So
how does that fit with רבי שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabi Shimon ben
Gamliel? סו אמר רב פפא רצו חודש רצו שלשים יום. so amar
Rav Papa ratzu chodesh ratzu shloshim yom. He doesn't mean it only
can be twenty-nine. He means you can choose to make אדר שני
Adar Sheni either twenty-nine or thirty. אוקיי, okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says, תא חזי מה איכא בין תקיפיא קדמאי לענוותנותיא בתראי. tacha zi
ma ika bein takifaya kadmaya l'invatnusaya batrayei. Come see the difference between
the mighty early ones and the humble later ones. Why? Because that
statement because it says, where was he, because תניא tanya that was
a statement
by
רבי שמעון... Rabi Shimon... 29 or 30. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel said the matter is good is good in our
eyes in order to add the year. So he basically he was
using the royal we, but he basically was saying like I have
seen fit to add this extra month. So that was he was
the humble later generation. He was the son of רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel. and he was speaking in a non-modest tone. I mean it
was the royal we, but he was saying I we have seen
fit to add this extra month. Now compare that to his father,
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel, דתניא De-tanya we taught in a ברייתא Baraita
and if you remember רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel he was the one
that would throw around his, you know, political weight. He was the
one that made רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua come to him on רבי
יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? He was the one
that made a point of showing like I'm the נשיא Nasi and
I have the authority and you've got to listen to me. So
the גמרא Gemara is going to say the irony that רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל said I've added the extra month. Whereas רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel the father who presumably was one that was more about the
authority of the נשיא, Nasi, he's going to say I and my
colleagues have added the extra month.
Okay, yes. Is it just that the Aramaic formulation is in the
תוספתא Tosefta itself?
Oh, it's in the תוספתא Tosefta itself?
Oh, it's
a much longer version of it? Interesting. Yeah, that we've that we've
preserved the record of it in Aramaic too. Yeah, right. Well they
spoke Aramaic in the Tannaitic period. It just wasn't the language the
formal literary language, but presumably here it's being recorded, right, I mean
Eli makes an excellent point. It's not like they only spoke Aramaic
later. It's that the formal language of issuing rabbinic statements was in
Mishnaic Hebrew. But here we're but they spoke Palestinian Aramaic. So here
we're preserving the language of the official edict. Okay, so let's just
finish this up. דתניא De-tanya מעשה ברבן גמליאל שהיה יושב על גבי
מעלה בהר הבית Ma'aseh be-Rabban Gamliel she-hayah yoshev al gabei ma'aleh be-Har
HaBayit he was sitting on one of the steps in הר הבית,
Har HaBayit, והיה יוחנן סופר הלז עומד לפניו, Ve-hayah Yochanan Sofer Hallaz
omed lefanav, יוחנן Yochanan his scribe was there, ושלש אגרות חתוכות לפניו
Ve-shalosh igrot chatuchot lefanav
and he had three letters already apparently like the cloth was cut
out, מונחות. munachot. אמר טול איגרתא חדא tolli itgarta chada take one
of these pieces of cloth וכתוב ve-chotuv and write the following. לאחנא
בני גלילא עילאה לאחנא בני גלילא תתאה Le-achana benei Galila illa'ah le-achana
benei Galila tatta'ah to our brothers in the upper Galilee and the
lower Galilee, שלמכון ישגא Shelomchon yisge
let your peace be increased, מהודעין אנן לכון Mehode'in anan lechon
we are informing you דזמן ביעורא מטא di-zman bi'ura mata the time
of ביעור bi'ur like every three years you have to get rid
of all the מעשר ma'aser in your house, that time is coming,
לאפרושי מעשרא ממעטנא דזיתא Leafrushei ma'asra mi-ma'atana de-zeita
you have to now take מעשר ma'aser from your sort of your
piles of olives because in the Galilee olives was the major crop.
Okay so that was one letter he issued. וטול איגרתא חדא Ve-tolli
itgarta chada and then he said take another letter וכתוב ve-chotuv and
this he's talking to his scribe, write the following. לאחנא בני דרומא
Le-achana benei daroma to our brothers in the south, שלמכון ישגא Shelomchon
yisge let your peace be increased, much blessings to you, מהודעין אנן
לכון Mehode'in anan lechon
we inform you דזמן ביעורא מטא di-zman bi'ura mata the time of
the of the destroying of the getting rid of the מעשר ma'aser
has come, לאפרושי מעשרא מאומרי שבלא Leafrushei ma'asra mi-umrei shivla to take
מעשר ma'aser from the from the from the
crops of what do you call it from the bundles of wheat.
So because in the because in the south it was more wheat
than it was olives. Okay. Now and now our point is the
third letter. וטול איגרתא חדא Ve-tolli itgarta chada take one letter וכתוב
ve-chotuv and write the following. לאחנא בני גלוותא בבבל Le-achana benei galvasa
be-Bozel to our brethren in the exile in Babylonia ולאחנא דבמדיי ve-le-achana
de-vi-madai and in and in מדיי Madai ולשאר כל גלוותא דישראל ve-lish'ar
kol galvuta de-Yisrael and to all of the exile you know places
of exile of Israel. This is so fascinating. It's like a historical
document, right? It's so different from everything else. Okay. שלמכון ישגא לעלם
Shelomchon yisge le-alam may you have much peace
forever. Interesting to add the word לעלם le-alam here. מהודעין אנן לכון
Mehode'in anan lechon we inform you דגוזליא רקיקין de-gozalaya rakikin the
the birds are tender ואימריא עדקין ve-imraya adkin and the and the
flock are small וזמנא דאביבא לא מטא ve-zimna de-aviva lo mata the
time of the אביב Aviv has not yet come ושפרא מילתא באנפיי
ובאנפי חבריי ve-shafra milta be-anpai u-ve-anpei chaverai
and the matter is good in my in to me and to
my colleagues ואוסיפת על שתא דא יומין תלתין ve-osifat al shatta da
yomin tlatin and we've added 30 days. So how could this be?
רבן גמליאל who was always about showing the power of the נשיא
and emphasizing you know the submission of the people under him, how
come here he's speaking in this more humble term? So the גמרא
Gemara says דילמא בתר דעברוה. dilma batar de-avruha. Well maybe this took
place after because he threw around his weight too much. You remember
the story that for a time he was taken out of being
the נשיא. So after that he he learned his lesson to be
a little bit more humble. Now it might just be he learned
a lesson but תוספות Tosafot has one sentence here in תוספות, Tosafot,
בתר דעברוה batar de-avruha תוספות Tosafot says פירוש דהיה לו חבר רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה שהיה נשיא עמו. peirush de-hayah lo chaver Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya she-hayah nasi imo. It wasn't he just was choosing to
speak in a more humble term. After that event Event, he had
a co-leader. He actually wasn't alone. It was after that event, he
was always partnered. Okay, לכן אמר באנפי חברי. L'chen amar b'antei chavrei.
So, very interesting in terms of that, but the whole issue about
the authority of the נשיא and tomorrow we're going to see about,
so we've had about appointment and authority of the נשיא, the third
thing we saw in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, which we're going to see
tomorrow in the בבלי Bavli is going to be about the centrality
of ארץ ישראל. Okay. So, we got a lot done today. יישר
כח. Yasher Koach.